Welcome back. Now that you understand primitive types and type inference, it's time to
level up our knowledge with arrays and tuples. These are essentially tools for working with
collections of data in TypeScript. Whether we're storing a list of names or a pair of coordinates,
TypeScripts are going to help us keep things organized as well as type safe.
So first of all, let's talk about arrays. So let's just remind ourselves what are arrays exactly?
Well an array is a list of values all of the same type and TypeScript lets us to clear what kind of
values array should contain. So let's say for example we're going to create an array of routes.
So we just give it a colon and we say this is an array of string which we do by doing the type
string and then the two square brackets. And then we can define that array as a list of strings.
So apple and banana and cherry. And of course all these items in array
are the same type of string which is for string. Let's now work at how we can to store an array
of numbers for example. So we can do say scores. We say this is a type of number. There's an array
an array of numbers and then we can define the numbers in array say 85 92 and 78.
And let's do another example and this time we're going to create an array of flags.
The flags are going to be Boolean to Boolean an array. Let me set that array so you say true,
false and true.
Now that's one way of declaring arrays that is actually an alternative
array or declaring arrays and that is used a generic syntax and it looks like this.
Let's say for example we have an array of cities and rather than saying string like this we can
say array and then give it a type in ankle brackets an array of string and then we define our strings
just exactly like we did before. So we can say like London for example and Paris.
And of course if we wanted to do numbers we could just just change this ankle brackets to number.
And then we declare our array of numbers in the same way.
Type scripts of course is going to prevent us from adding the wrong type to an array.
So let's just for example just create an array of numbers.
So number I'm just going to do it the first way and we say an array of say 25 and 30.
And then if we try and modify that array let's say going to push something like a string to it.
It's going to give us an error it's going to say it's not possible to assign that parameter
to that array of course because it's an array of numbers but if we then change that to
any other number like 89 it's going to be quite happy with that. So it's protects our code from
unexpected bugs and it's going to make our data so much more predictable.
So let's just do a very quick big steer array challenge. Now this should be pretty straightforward.
Let's say we have some names and our strings and we have something like this.
Alice and say Bob.
Now check in here an error and of course we're going to get an error because we have a number
in a string array. So of course we can just simply fix this by removing the offending item
and it says we're going to put a string instead.
Now we talked about arrays let's now talk about tuple so it's UPLE.
So a tuple is just like an array but with a fixed length and specific types for each
position. So kind of think of it's a little bit like a mini data structure. So let's have a look
at what that look could look like. So if we're a user we want to store perhaps a string
the name and maybe the age so we could define a tuple of having two things so we could
store a string and also a number. So this could be a tuple happens to have the same square
brackets as an array but it's now a tuple because we've got two things in it.
We have a string of Alice and we can also store an array and you can see how this is a little
bit different syntax than the array because we actually specifying the first type and also the
second type which marries up with the string that we have here and also the number that we have here.
So each position in our tuple has a defined type and we can't swap or add elements
so we can't for example come in here and add another item to it because it's going to complain
because you should only have two and the fact that we've got three in here.
But we can also change the number of items in this particular tuple. We've got two to find here
but let's say for example we also want to store a boolean then as soon as we do that it's going
to complain because we haven't supplied that boolean so we could then come in here and make it happy
by giving it a boolean flag like true for example. So how do we actually modify our tuple where we
can simply give it the actual index of the thing we're trying to change. So let's say we want to
change the person's name we can do user and then zero so that corresponds to the very first
type inside our tuple. You'd say that is now Bob for example. We could also then change
into the actual image so we could do user one and we could change it to say 41 for example.
What are tuples used for? What sort of things? Well, they're particularly useful for things like
coordinates or maybe key value pairs or label data. Let's have an example. Now let's say for
example we want to store something like RGB, red, green and blue values. Now if we did something
like this we could say let RGB and then we'd say in brackets number number and number.
So let's say for example we want to store some values for red and blue and green and any color.
And if we think we could do it this way we could think we could do let's red equals RGB
and then specify the colors and brackets maybe like 23, 45 and 56. But we can think at an error
saying it's a reverse value rather than type. So this is a nice idea. How exactly do we do this?
Well we can use the keyword type. So rather than this but how using let because it thinks it's
a natural value here what we do instead is we define RGB as a type of tuple which we do type
with this and rather than colon we change that to an equal sign. This means we know to find an
RGB type and now we can create like an instance of that type and say red is a type of RGB
and it might be 255, 0 and 0 and maybe what to do like blue and blue is type of RGB
and that would be something like 0, 0 and 255 for example. So you can now see that in TypeScript
which is a kind of defining our own custom type and we're defining it as a tuple or where we specify
the types all that produce particular things and then we can then create variables based on that type
and then set the value accordingly. So arrays and tuples help us to manage collections
and structure data with confidence. So arrays are flexible lists of one type,
one of tuples are rigid structures with multiple types. In the next lesson we're going to explore
inums and literal types and these are tuals that help us to find strict sets of values that
make our code even more expressive.